NATHAN MATHER

PHD ECONOMIST

CONTACT

608-774-7648 njmather@umich.edu NathanMather.com

1181 Kay Pkwy, Ann Arbor, MI 48103

EDUCATION

2017-Present
PhD Candidate in Economics
University of Michigan - Ann Arbor
Public Finance
Labor Economics

2019

Masters in Economics University of Michigan - Ann Arbor

2016

Bachelor of Arts
University of Wisconsin - Madison
Economics (Honors)
Mathematics
Political Science

SKILLS

||| SOFTWARE

Expert: R (data.table, tidyverse, etc), Stata

Proficient: Github, Latex

Familiar: Python, Matlab, Julia, C++

Other: Unreal Engine, Premier Pro, Audition

||| PERSONAL SKILLS

Causal Inference, Economic Modeling, Process

Automation, Team Collaboration, Interactive Data

Visualization, Public Speaking, Web Scraping

PROFILE

During my time as a PhD candidate in economics, I have built on and solidified the fundamental skills I gained as an undergraduate and research analyst. My research projects developed key skills that are invaluable to a challenging and fast paced analytic career. For example, I tackle difficult questions by finding new innovative solutions. Measuring utility is a task that has eluded economists since the 18th century. By approaching this question in a new way, I provide an answer using a simple model and survey data. Additionally, I identify the most efficient approach to achieve a goal. I show how the common practice of measuring average test score gains can be improved by measuring the impact on both struggling and excelling students separately. This same insight applies to a wide range of problems. The most important skill I have gained, however, is the ability to independently learn what I need for the task at hand, whatever that may be.

EXPERIENCE

2017-Present

PHD CANDIDATE

University of Michigan- Ann Arbor

- Acquired training in causal inference, statistics, public finance, industrial organization estimation techniques, and economic modeling
- Perfected public speaking and communication in formal seminars
- Experienced with acquiring grants and running surveys
- Worked independently to solve complex problems

2016-2017

RESEARCH ANALYST

Education Analytics - Madison Wisconsin

- Mastered R programming for data cleaning, analysis and visualization
- Developed best practices for cooperation among team members
- Gained task automation experience
- Contributed to in-house packages and tools

2018 - 2020

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Education Policy Initiative (Brian Jacob) - University of Michigan

- Mastered data manipulation using Stata
- Improved yearly data intake using process automation
- Created R training materials

2018-2022

GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR

University of Michigan- Ann Arbor

- Trained students in complex quantitative methods
- · Communicated complex ideas using simple intuition and examples
- Presented lengthy readings and research using manageable key ideas
- Improved my own writing through grading student work